Finding Aid for the John Carl Parish Papers LSC.0121
UCLA Library Special Collections
John Carl Parish papers
1915-1939
UCLA Library Special Collections
Parish, John Carl
LSC.0121
13.5 linear feet (27 boxes and 29 oversize boxes)
John Carl Parish (1881-1939) was a history professor who taught at Colorado College, the State University of Iowa, and UCLA. He edited the State Historical Society of Iowa's monthly journal, The Palimpsest (1920-22), the Proceedings of the Southern California Historical Society, and the Pacific Historical Review. His published books include Robert Lucas (1907), George Wallace Jones (1912), and The Man with the Iron Hand (1913). The collection consists of bibliography cards, typed transcripts and film reproductions of manuscripts, and note cards of document and manuscript material relating to the colonial period and westward movement in American history, with special emphasis on the 18th century and sources in French.
Restrictions on Access
Portions of collection unprocessed. Some material in the collection are unavailable for access. Please contact Special Collections reference (AskLSC@library.ucla.edu) for more information.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942335533606533
Biography
Parish was born on July 25, 1881 in Des Moines, Iowa; Ph.D, State University of Iowa, 1908; assistant professor of history, 1914, and in 1915, professor of history, Colorado College; after serving in World War I, he was lecturer in history at the State University of Iowa, 1920-22; assistant professor, 1922-24, associate professor, 1924-27, and professor of history, UCLA; edited the State Historical Society of Iowa's monthly journal, The Palimpsest, 1920-22; later edited the Proceedings of the Southern California Historical Society, and in 1932 became editor of the Pacific Historical Review; published books include Robert Lucas (1907), George Wallace Jones (1912), and The Man with the Iron Hand (1913); he died on January 13, 1939 in Los Angeles.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of research materials of UCLA history professor John Carl Parish. Includes bibliography cards, typed transcripts and film reproductions of manuscripts, and note cards of document and manuscript material relating to the colonial period and westward movement in American history, with special emphasis on the 18th century and sources in French.
Historians -- United States -- Archives.; Parish, John Carl -- Archives; University of California, Los Angeles. Department of History--Faculty -- Archives
- English Files
  Scope and Contents note
  A Listing of Bound Volumes upon whose contents notes have been distributed in Dr. Parish's Files.
  - 1. American Historical Review vol.21, 23, 28, and 38.
    General note
    (2 carbon sets in office file)
  - 2. Brock, Dinwidde Records, 1-2.
    (1 carbon set in office file)
  - 3. Coll. Georgia Historical Society.
    (1 set in chronological file - documents, English or Spanish)
    1 set filed topically and 1 set in office file.
  - 4. Louisiana Historical Quarterly, vol.1-17 (English items, except 3 and 9).
    (2 carbon sets in office files)
    (Miss Lilley indicates the vol.3 and 9 missing from UCLA Library)
  - 5. Mereness' Travels
    Complete - in chronological order (English items).
    (2 carbon sets in office files, 1 set lacking 4 cards)
  - 6. Mississippi Valley Historical Review, 1-21 () Except vol.16., 1935
    (2 carbon sets in office file, 1 set lacking for vol.19-20)
  - 7. New York Colonial Documents, 1-21 () Except vol.16., 1935
  - 8. North Carolina Colonial Records, vol.III-VI.
  - 9. North Carolina Historical Review, vol.1-10.
    (2 carbon sets for 1-5 in office file, no duplicates for 6-10)
  - 10. South Carolina Gazette.
    Items from, In North Carolina Historical Comm.
  - 11. South Carolina Historical and Genealogical Magazine, no.1-35 (), 1934
    Except pp.1-119 - no.1, missing from library.
  - 12. Virginia Magazine of History and Biography, vol.1-41 (), 1933
    (2 carbon sets for vol.7-41; 1 carbon set for 50-56 in office file)
  - 13. Virginia Magazine of History and Biography, vol.1-41 (), 1933
  - 14. Wisconsin Historical Society Collections, vol.16-18.
    English items after 1763 in English files.
  - 15. Wisconsin Magazine of History, no.1-18 (), 1934
  - 16. Michigan Pioneer and Historical Collection, vol.19 (), covering 1761-1781
    (2 carbons in office file)
- French Files
  French items from volumes indicated above in English Files: 4., 5., 13., 14., 15., 16.
  - 1. Margry 1-6.
    (No duplicates)
  - 2. Mississippi Provincial Archives - French Dominion 1-3.
  - 3. New York Colonial Documents, vol.9: pp.704-1112; and vol.10.
    (2 carbons sets for vol.9; no duplicates for vol.10)
  - 4. Surrey - selected items., 1730-1739
    (1 carbon set in office files)
- [Handwritten File Listing]
  - File Drawer 1
    - [Folder with outline of card classification system].
    - Dr. Koontz, etc., 4 photos in envelope.
      Old maps.
    - French Archives, (16 folders)
      - ., n.d., 1750-1763, 1768; Typewritten (carbons).
        French [some with English translations attached].
        1755 (2 folders)
        1756 (2 folders)
    - French Archives., 1733-1763
      - Guide to Bibliotheque Nationale, 1925.
      - Report on transcription of documents from French Archives by Waldo G. Leland [?] [Report of Librarian of Congress:
    - [Not in File Folder]
      - Letter, in Spanish (English translation), sent by M. l'Abbe de Frischmen.., 17 September 1756; 169pp. typed [carbon].
      - Letter, in Spanish (French translation), sent by M. l'Abbe de Frischmen.., 17 September 1756; 111pp. typed [carbon].
    - Ft. Carlos III, (Arkansas Post)., 1783; 12pp. typed (carbon)
      Spanish account of attack by Colbert.
    - Mormon Diary., Original and carbon of copy. 45pp.
      Diary of Lorenzo Don Young.
    - Sir Thomas Robinson's instructions to Braddock.., 1755; 2 typewritten copies of letters.
    - Arthur Dubbs to Glen.., 1755
      re boundary between North Carolina & South Carolina.
    - Lyttelton [?] Material., Four communiques typed (carbon) without[?] cards attached.
    - Ring Notebook (Spanish) with letters., Contains typed (original) copies. 147pp., plus 15pp. in English.
    - Nevin, Rogers Ponteach.
      - Book printed in Chicago, The Coxton [?] Club.., 1914; Original typed copy, 179pp.
    - Floor no.22., Typed - original and carbon - 5pp. each.
      - Letter from Lyttelton [?] to the Board.
    - Floor no.2., Typewritten - some original, some carbon.
      - Communications of James Crockett and others, South Carolina.., 1747, 1749
    - Vaudreuil [?] III, dated (French)., 1743; Letterbooks. 90pp., typewritten (original).
      (Says - Folios 1-24 copied by Carpenter - not yet verified)
      - [Hunt. Lib. Lo. 9 III]
    - Manuel Lisa and Captive boys, corr. in res. [?] Felipe Enerio de Mes., 6 photostatic copies.
    - Hortley.
      - Letter dated - Hortley to Carmorthen [?]., 1785; Photostatic copy. 16pp.
    - Marin Journal [], 1753-1754; 105pp. yellow paper - written in pencil.
    - Marin, 106pp. - typed, carbon, Journal of M. Marin file
    - Marin Journal, Original typecopy. 107pp. typed, originals (of foregoing)
    - ----- -----., Another copy, 106pp. with numbering changed in pencil.
    - The Seige of Fort London.., 1760; Typed (original) 14pp.
    - Robertson.
      - Report of Colonel James Robertson to General Goge [?].., 1764; Typed (carbon); 32pp.
      - Also typed note re numbering of pages - signed Carpenter.
    - Margery [?] - Catlin [?].
      - Letters signed by Catlin [?]., 11pp. Photostatic copies.
    - Margery [?] - Parkinson.
      - Letter signed by Francis Parkinson (with notes in French)., 3pp. Photostatic copies.
      - Transcript of Parkinson's letter., Original and carbon, 2pp.
      - Transcript of notes (in French) by Margery [?]., Original and carbon.
      - Notes by Margery [?]., Manuscript copy (2 original and 1 carbon) and typed copies.
    - Couture.
      - Map of Rio Grande and Mississippi., Photo.
    - Bernard Romans.
      - [Bernard Romans to Dr. Williamson] Boston.., December 20, 1773; Transcript - original and carbon.
      - Letter [B. Romans ?], New York.., November 6, 1773; Manuscript copy.
    - Research.
      - Library of Congress film, Maurepos [?] to Vandreuil [?].., 1746; 3pp, 2pp. In envelope.
      - Nouveaux Voyages dans L'Amerique Systemtrionale [?], Charguion [?]. - University of Arb. Library [?], 1775; Transcript (typed, original and carbon) 9pp.
      - Resume of Antonio del Reio El Conde de Aronda [?] in Revista Espanola de Ambos Mundos III, Madrid., 1855; Transcript (typed, original and carbon) 5pp.
      - List of bound volumes upon whose contents notes have been distributed in Dr. parish's file.
      - Minutes des lettres scrittes a las Mobile....., 1743; Photostat of letters. Typed on yellow sheet.
    - Atkin Report 1954-5 (Huntington Library), Original typed transcript. 184pp. Not in folder.
    - Stuart Index., Photostatic copy (less than original size). In box.
    - Mease.
      - Narrative of a Journey through several parts of the Province of West Florida, in the years 1770 and 1771 by Edward Mease., Transcript (typed and original, carbon) 50pp.
    - Box.
      - Original Mease narrative., Photostatic copy.
    - Public Record Office of England - Foreign correspondence - America.., 1783; Transcript - typed original & carbon. In black envelope.
    - Historical account of the Revolt of the Chartam [?] Indians [Br. Mus. Lans. 809 ff. 1-3 vo.]., Transcript (typed original). Not in folder.
  - British Museum
    - Br. Mus. Continued.., 20 January 1753; Holograph and photostatic copies.
      Contains copies of Council Journal of 1748, etc.
      Also handwritten copy of message which Governor Glen refused to receive.
      continued ff 19-33 vo. Atkin
    - Br. Mus, P.10771 9 pp. Atkin to BT. and MS 38334., 24 June 1762; Typed copies (original and carbon) made from photostatic copies in file.
  - British Colonial Affairs
    - Letters and documents and/or transcripts of letters and documents.., 1732-1771; Photostats.
  - Ind. Rec. Bh [?]
    - Documents., 1750-1758, n.d.; Photostats.
  - 4 File Folders of Maps
    - 23 letters and documents (French).., 2nd half of 17th century; Photostats.
    - O'Fallon.
      - Transcripts - [mostly carbon] - letters to Carondelet or from him. - Spanish., 1792-1794
    - O'Fallon.
      - Photostat of letter dated signed by James O'Fallon [English], May 18, 1790
    - Mormons.
      - Journal of Henry Stondarge [?].., 1896-1897; Transcript, 39pp., typed [carbon copy].
    - Folder (No Name on it)
      Contains typewritten notes on the Largo Map of West Florida, etc., in the Gages [?] papers.
    - Folder (Unlabeled)
      - List of pages sent to Mr. Parish.., January 20, 1928; (carbon copy) 13 items.
      - (No title) beginning, I arrived in Charleston, the metropolis of South Carolina, the 9th of December 1958., Mimeographed sheet.
    - Stuart to Dartmouth, Aug 5, 1773
      - Culled [?] Virginia - Cherokee Line, Donelson [?] Survey.., 1771; 3pp. typed [original].
      - Virginia - Cherokee Line. Donelson [?] Survey notes.., 1771; 1p. typed (carbon).
      - Maps., 2 sheets yellow paper written pencil notes and 7 typewritten sheets (original).
      - General List., 27 typewritten sheets (original).
    - Smith, Jedediah [?]
      - Letters loaned by Miss Dunn [?], relative to J. Smith., Copies.
      - Bibliography - Jedediah [?] Strong Smith (USC).
      - Excerpt from Indian Tribes of the U.S. by Henry R. Schoolcraft., 1p. typewritten
      - Bond signed by Jedediah [?] S. Smith at Monterey.., 15 November 1827; Carbon copy.
    - French Archives
      - Letters written by Salmon.., 1753; Typewritten [originals and carbon] on white and yellow paper.
    - Archives, orders, etc.
      Penciled and typed lists.
  - Hunt, L.
    - Letter written by Aaron Buer [?], Folder with typewritten copy [original].
    - Godson to Greene.., 7 December 1851
      - Letter from James Gadsden to General Thomas Jefferson Green dated.., December 7, 1851; Typed copy (carbon) 6pp.
    - Vaudreüil., Transcript (typewritten, original).
      - Vaudreüil to Derneuille. (French)., 1744
      - Vaudreüil to Derneuille and Hazeur. (French)., 1745
      - Vaudreüil to Derneuille and Hazeur. (French)., 1746
      - Vaudreüil to Derneuille and de Velle. (French)., 1747; (Folder with carbon copies).
    - Vaudreüil to de Velle.
      Contains originals (and carbon copy) of typed transcripts of letters. dated 1944 (French).
    - Vaudreüil 1-24 complete., Typed transcript (carbon) - 90pp.
      - Letters - Vaudreüil to de Bauchomp.., 1743; Typed transcript (carbon).
    - Vaudreüil - extracts, etc. dated., 1742-1752; Typed transcript (original) of excerpts, in English - 55pp.
    - Synopses of French letters 1742-1752., Photostats - 76pp. and carbon, typed transcript of same - of marginal notes in English.
    - Atkin to B.J.., 30 May 1755; Photostatic copies - 55pp.
    - Atkin Observations.., March 8 [1756]; 4pp. Photostatic copy.
    - Atkin to Gist., 12pp. Photostatic copy.
    - Atkin to Gist., 12pp. Photostatic copy.
    - Atkin - List of Goods.., 1757; 5pp. Photostatic copy.
    - Atkin to Loudouni [?].., March 26, 1757; 2pp. Photostatic copy.
    - Atkin to Cunnicahtorky [?].., August 4, 1757; 4pp. Photostatic copy.
    - Atkin - reward & list of goods.., October 1757; 4pp. Photostatic copy.
    - Atkin to Loudrun [?].., October 8, 1759; 4pp. Photostatic copy.
    - Atkin's representations against Indian Trade.., 1758; 11pp. Photostatic copy and typed transcript (original) 9pp.
    - Atkin to Clerk of Council.., January 26, 1758; 4pp. Photostatic copy.
    - Atkin to Byrd.., March 24, 1758; 2pp. Photostatic copy.
    - Atkin to Byrd.., March 24, 1758; 1p. Photostatic copy.
    - Atkin to Byrd.., March 24, 1758; 2pp. Photostatic copy.
    - Atkin to Loudoun.., March 25, 1758; 3pp. Photostatic copy.
    - Atkin to Loudoun.., March 25, 1758; 4pp. Photostatic copy.
    - Atkin to Loudoun.., April 1, 1758; 2pp. Photostatic copy.
    - Charles Rohr to ....., March 26, 1758; 2pp. Photostatic copy.
    - French Agression in N.A.., [c. 1756]; 7pp. Photostatic copy and typescript of some (original & carbon, 8pp.).
    - Hunt L. Governor, to Randolph and Byrd.., February and March 1756; 43pp. Photostatic copy.
    - Atkin to Loudoun.., May 14, 1756; 4pp. Photostatic copy.
    - Instructions proposed by Atkins for himself.., probably 1756; 6pp. Photostatic copy and typescript (typed original) 9pp.
    - Atkin to Loudoun.., October 6, 1756; 2pp. Photostatic copy.
    - Atkin to Loudoun.., October 20, 1756; 2pp. Photostatic copy.
    - Notes from Captured French documents.., November-December 1756; 6pp. Photostatic copy.
      [Apparently English translaton of notes taken from captured French documents - Deals largely with movement of ships]
    - Atkin to Loudoun.., November 26, 1756; 15pp. Photostatic copy and transcript - [typed, original] 18pp.
    - French Document.., 15 January 1944; 13pp. Photostatic copies and 8pp. [carbon] typed transcript.
    - Atkin - Choctau [?] Renalt.., 20 January 1753; 37pp. Photostatic copy.
    - Choctau [?].., 15 January 1756; Transcript [Typed original] - 8pp.
    - Denividdic [?] letters in re Atkin., Transcript [typed, original and carbon] - pages and pages unnumbered.
    - Keith to ....., October 1744; Transcript [typed, original and carbon].
    - Keith to ....., October 1744; Transcript [5pp. typed, original and carbon].
  - French Archives
    - Diron to Maurepas.., 15 August 1730; 15pp. photographed.
    - Crement to Maurepas.., 23 December 1731; 8pp. photographed.
    - Estat des Marchandes.., 23 December 1731; 3pp. photographed.
    - Crement to Maurepas.., 15 March 1732; 3pp. photos.
    - Crement to Maurepas.., 6 June 1732; 6pp. photos.
    - Diron to Maurepas.., 30 March 1734; 5pp. photos.
    - Diron to Maurepas.., 15 July 1734; 6pp. photos.
    - Diron to Maurepas.., 1 September 1734; 10pp. photos.
    - Diron to Maurepas.., September 1734; 10pp. photos.
    - ----.., April 13, 1746; 3pp. photos - copies of letters.
      Copies of letters, from Maurepas to Vandre¨il.
    - Diron to Maurepas.., 22 September 1734; 2pp. photos. and more photos.
    - ., 22 September, 1734; 3 folders. 2pp. photos.
      Followed by folders containing typescripts of French letters - [in French, some translations into English made from A.E. Angl.(?) fims].
  - Stuart
    - Correspondence and reports - Stuart.., 1770-1761; Folders containing copies.
  - Boxes - Card Files
    - 1A
      American History Magazine
      American Historical Review
      Canadian Historical Review
      Catholic Historical Review
      Eastern Tennessee Historical Society Publication
      Franco-American Review
      Georgia Historical Society Coll.[?]
      Hispanic American Historical Review
      Journal of Southern History
      Kansas Historical Quarterly
    - 1B
      Same [as 1A] except Georgia Historical Society Coll. missing.
    - 2A
      Louisiana Historical Quarterly
      Michigan and Pioneer
      Hist Cal.[?]
      Mississippi Historical Society
      Mississippi Valley Historical Review
    - 2B
      Same [as 2A] except Mississippi Valley Historical Review, vol.6-15 missing.
    - 3A
      Missouri Historical Review
      Michigan Historical Society Records
      New Mexico Historical Review
      North Carolina Historical Review
      Ohio State Archaeological and Historical Quarterly
      Oregon Historical Quarterly
      Pacific Historical Review
      Pacific Northwest Quarterly
      Pennsylvania History
    - 3B
      Same [as 3A] except North Carolina Historical Review, vol.6 missing.
    - 4A
      South Carolina Historical and Genealogical Magazine
      Southwestern Historical Quarterly
      Virginia Magazine of History and Biography
    - 4B
      Same [as 4A] except Virginia Magazine of History and Biography, vol.1-6 [sic] missing.
    - 5A
      Western Pennsylvania History Magazine
      Collections of the State Historical Society of Wisconsin, vol.16-18
      Wisconsin Magazine of History
      Colonial Record of North Carolina
    - 5B
      Western Pennsylvania History Magazine (missing)
      Collections of the State Historical Society of Wisconsin, vol.16 (vol.17-18 missing)